Let's take a look at this oscillating
spring.
We can actually use energy to map this
out,
and we can use energy to basically solve a
lot
of problems involving time, speed, and
potential
energy. Usually the question will want us
to
calculate something like its speed, its
fastest
possible speed. And now you have this
image
in mind. This is what they mean by an
oscillating
spring. Let's map this out using time.
So let's say the spring is first initially
at
its highest peak, so all the way down
here.
And then it goes a bit up, and this would
be
the spring at its equilibrium, which means
it
would be the spring at rest. And then, as
you
can see, as you saw in the diagram, it's
going
to go up beyond equilibrium for a bit, and
then
it's going to repeat the process all over
again.
So it's going to go up, up, and then it's
going
to go down, and then back down.
So that's basically the motion of the
spring.
Now, what you notice is if you just mapped
the
velocity out of the block, well, this over
here
would have a velocity of zero, and this
would
also have a velocity of zero, and this
be in motion. Let's just call this
velocity
x for now, for simplicity's sake.
And why is it that these two have a
velocity
of zero? When you see over here, when they
change
direction, the velocity kind of stops.
It stops moving for a split second, and
then
it goes in the other direction. Well,
that's
when energy comes into play. We have
learned
that — I'll erase this — we have learned
that
the total mechanical energy of the system,
E
total, is the sum of the kinetic energy
and
the potential energy. Now, if kinetic
energy,
as we know, is the energy based off of
motion,
if v equals zero, then that means that
there's
no kinetic energy. So at these two points,
let's
call this point one, point two, point
three,
at point one and three, all the energy is
potential
energy. All the energy is potential
energy.
However, at point two, when it's
at point two, all the energy is
kinetic energy. So between these points,
between
one and two, and between two and three,
let's
say, for example, at this point, the box
is
still going up. It has a velocity, it has
kinetic
energy going up, but it's not at its
fastest
speed. There's still potential energy
because
there's still a force driving it up, and
that's
the restoring force, as we learned. So if
at
two, kinetic energy is at max because all
the
total mechanical energy is kinetic energy,
then
we can say that at point two, the speed is
—
or the means it would
be faster because one over two mv squared,
as
we know. And that is basically how we map
out
energy. Now, we know that, let's say, this
box
has a mass of m. The kinetic energy will
be
one over two mv squared. We know that.
We've learned that equals one over two mv
squared.
But what is potential energy? We've only
learned
about gravitational potential energy. We
haven't
really touched on elastic potential
energy.
And I don't know if I've said this before
in
the energy thing. I think I saved it for
this
video. The elastic potential energy is
given
as one over two kx squared.
And you know all the variables — spring
constant
and displacement from equilibrium.
And this is basically a very, very crucial
formula
that we can use. Now, we can use this to
solve
a lot of problems because we know that, at
equilibrium,
this will be all the energy that remains.
And at either points one or three, at the
turning
points, this will be the only type of
energy
that remains — only potential energy.
Now, you might be wondering about energy.
We've learned that you could be
gravitational
potential energy as well. So if there's
potential energy, then why are we ignoring
it?
Well, the gravitational potential energy
can
be ignored because it's very, very close
to
being constant for all of these scenarios.
A spring won't be that massive. So at
point
one, point two, and point three, it's safe
to
say that the gravitational potential
energy
is constant. So if we map out and do our
calculations, it's just going to cancel
out.
That's why mostly we ignore gravitational
potential
energy. So in spring systems, unless
there's
a net external force or another major key
factor
that moves the object, you will only be
dealing
with kinetic energy of the block or the
object
and the potential elastic energy.
Now, let's see a question.
Over here, I have a question. And this is
a
question that must need energy to be
solved.
And if you get energy, if you get that
unit,
this is a really, really easy question.
And
if you get what I just said over here. So
physics
is really just understanding what you're
doing.
Practice won't help everything. You
actually
have to understand what's happening.
And once you understand it, maybe not the
first
time. I definitely did not get it the
time. I took two sets of classes doing the
same
thing. But when it clicks, you're going to
get
the question right every, every single
time.
So really try your hardest to understand
these.
And if you don't get what I'm saying, you
could
search it up, ask AI, because AI is
actually
a really, really good tool to ask if you
don't
understand something, because it gives you
personalized
answers. But this question will just do it
right
now. A 0.8 kilogram mass is attached to a
horizontal
spring with a spring constant of 400.
The spring is compressed by 0.12 metres
and
released from rest and calculate the
maximum
speed of the mass.
Well, let's map it out. I'm just going to
real
quick borrow the diagram we drew over here
and
we can label our values.
So really does not matter which way it's
compressed.
If it's compressed like this or it's
stretched,
really does not matter. But for the sake
of
the question, we'll just treat it as it's
compressed.
If this was equilibrium, then x over here
or
the compressed would be 0.12 metres.
So in order to know the maximum speed, we
will
need the kinetic energy because that's the
only
thing that has the speed.
So k equals one over two mv squared.
Now, as we've talked about, the maximum
speed
is always in the middle of the turning
points
or aka equilibrium. So the total
mechanical energy initially is equal to
the
end because the law of conservation of
energy.
Initially, as we've talked about, there is
only
potential energy because it's released
from
rest. There's no kinetic energy, but there
is
a lot of potential elastic energy.
How do we calculate that? We use our
formula
over here, one over two kx squared.
So I'll just explain it.
ue plus kei equals kef at equilibrium plus
uef at equilibrium.
There is no potential energy at
equilibrium
and there is no kinetic energy initially.
So what we're left with is ue equals kef.
Now, we can just plug in our formula, one
over
two kx squared. So one over two kx squared
equals
one over two mv squared.
And v will be the velocity at equilibrium.
We can cancel out these terms. We know k
is
400. 400 times 0.12 squared equals the
mass
is 0.80 v squared.
So v would be equal to root 400 times 0.12
squared
over 0.80.
And when you solve that, you get v equals
2.7
metres per second. And that will be your
final
velocity. So as you can see, you can use
energy
to solve for velocity and a lot of other
values
as well. You need to use the conservation
of
energy and you need to remember three
things
or these things.
The turning point's velocity is zero and
that
means that the total mechanical energy is
equal
to the total potential energy. However, in
the
middle at equilibrium, all the total
mechanical
energy is equal to the total kinetic
energy
and there is no potential energy. And once
we
know that, we can easily use our
conservation
of energy to solve for whatever we want.
And we can also know this formula and this
formula
is useful because it literally depicts the
potential
energy of a spring. Gravitational
energy in these types of questions can
mainly
be ignored because it's usually constant
or
not big enough to do a lot of things.
Another thing is they might ask you a
question
for the speed in the middle of its path.
So let's say we have a mass that's not at
the
turning point, not at equilibrium, it's at
middle. And you can still use the
conservation
of energy to solve it. Let's say you're
given
this or this, doesn't matter, but when
you're
given one of these, let's say we're given
the
x and we're given also the spring
constant,
we can find the total mechanical energy.
And if it says the distance away from the
equilibrium,
for example, this would be y, then we can
easily
solve for the speed because what we can do
is
this is the initial total mechanical
energy
and using our formula, we know that 1 over
kx squared will equal to, and at this
point
it has both kinetic energy and potential
energy,
but we can calculate both of them if we
know
y over here. So it would be equal to,
let's
first do kinetic energy, 1 over 2 m v
squared,
v squared is what we wanted to calculate,
and
then 1 over 2 ky squared because
this would be the total mechanical energy
of
the system here. So it's still using
conservation
of energy, it's just slightly more
complicated
than the example we did here. And we can
simplify
it, I probably won't be doing that right
now,
but basically I've demonstrated that you
can
do it and I've showed you how.
And that's how you use energy to solve
these
questions. I hope you enjoyed and you
learned
how to do it, and I'll see you in the next
one.
Bye!